Finding Aid for the Lawrence H. Aller Papers LSC.0616
UCLA Library Special Collections
Lawrence H. Aller papers
1903-2001
UCLA Library Special Collections
Aller, Lawrence H.
LSC.0616
2 Linear Feet (2 cartons)
Lawrence H. Aller was an astronomer and professor at UCLA. The collection consists largely of correspondence and Aller's published papers on a variety of astronomical topics.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9947696453606533>
Biography/History
Lawrence H. Aller was born in Tacoma, WA on September 24, 1913. He developed an early interest in astronomy and, despite not graduating from high school, attended the University of California, Berkeley. After receiving his bachelor's degree, he attended Harvard, and earned his PhD in 1942. He taught at Indiana University and the University of Michigan and, in 1962, he became a professor at UCLA, where he remained for the rest of his career. During that time, he published six books and hundreds of scholarly articles, mostly dealing with gaseous nebulae and stellar atmospheres. He died in Los Angeles on March 16, 2003.
Scope and Content
The collection consists largely of reprints of Laurence Aller's scholarly publications, dozens of which appeared in a variety of journals spanning a period of more than sixty years. There is also a significant amount of correspondence with other astronomers, including Dorothy N. Davis-Locanthi, Donald Menzel, and Nicholas Mayall. Also present are observational data and lecture notes for "The Planetary Nebulae," a major project that Aller worked on from 1942-1975.
Organization and Arrangement
The collection is arranged in a single series, based on the work of the previous archivist.
Astronomers -- United States -- Archives.
- Aller, Lawrence H. - biographical and autobiographical material, circa 1943-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
- American Astronomical Society - Russell Lectureship, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Astronomy, 1933-1935 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Scope and Contents
  Contains handwritten notes and a typed manuscript, possibly from Aller's undergraduate days at Berkeley.
- Bok, Bart J., 1948-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Contains: letter from Bok, 1948; pamphlet "The Spiral Structure of Our Galaxy" [inscribed by Bok]; mimeograph "IAU Symposium No. 61 - Perth, W. Australia - New Problems in Astronomy - Summary and Conclusions."
- Correspondence, 1927-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Includes correspondence with Donald Menzel and J. H. Moore.
- Correspondence, 1931-1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Includes letter from Carl K. Seyfert, 1946 [with "Nuclear Emission in Spiral Nebulae"]; four letters from Dorothy N. Davis-Locanthi, 1976 [with "A Comparison of FeI Oscillator Strengths"]; handwritten letter from Donald Osterbrock, 1991.
- Correspondence, 1945-1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes correspondence with Leo Goldberg, Nicholas Mayall, Otto Struve, and Frank [Edmonson?].
- E-mail, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  Includes correspondence with Walter Feibelman.
- NASA - International Ultraviolet Explorer (IUE), 1979-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Proposals, 1967-1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Publications by Aller - master reprints, 1938-2001 (Box 1, Folder 13-21, Box 2, Folder 1-3)
- Publications by others, 1903-1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Scope and Content
  Contains: "An Example in Periodic Orbits" by James Park McCallie, 1903; "Temperature Determinations for Nuclei of Thirteen Planetary Nebulae" by H. Zanestra, 1960; "How to Become an Astronomer" by Freeman D. Miller, 1969.
- "The Planetary Nebulae", 1942-1975 (Box 2, Folder 5-9)
  Material for an ongoing project on planetary nebulae, consisting of observational data and lecture notes, in five binders.